So over the past few centuries, microscopes have revolutionized our world.
إذاً. خلال القرون القليلة الماضية، أحدثت المجاهر تغييراً لعالمنا
They revealed to us a tiny world of objects, life and structures
فقد أظهرت لنا الأجسام والحياة والتركيبات الدقيقة
that are too small for us to see with our naked eyes.
والتي من الصعوبة بمكان النظر إليها بالعين المجردة
They are a tremendous contribution to science and technology.
إنها مساهمة جبارة للعلم والتقنية
Today I'd like to introduce you to a new type of microscope,
اليوم... أريد أن أعرفكم على نوع جديد من المجهر
a microscope for changes.
مجهر للتغيير
It doesn't use optics like a regular microscope
إنه لا يستخدم الأضواء المرئية، مثل المجهر البسيط
to make small objects bigger,
لتكبير الأجسام الصغيرة،
but instead it uses a video camera and image processing
لكنه يستخدم بدلاً من ذلك كاميرا الفيديو مع معالجة الصور
to reveal to us the tiniest motions and color changes in objects and people,
ليكشف لنا أصغر تغيرات الحركات والألوان في الأجسام والبشر،
changes that are impossible for us to see with our naked eyes.
التغيرات المستحيل علينا إدراكها بالعين المجردة.
And it lets us look at our world in a completely new way.
والتي تسمح لنا بمشاهدة عالمنا بطريقة جديدة تماماً.
So what do I mean by color changes?
لذلك ما الذي أقصده بالتغيرات اللونية؟
Our skin, for example, changes its color very slightly
جلودنا على سبيل المثال تتغير ألوانها قليلاً جداً
when the blood flows under it.
عندما يتدفق الدم تحته.
That change is incredibly subtle,
هذا التغيير دقيق لا يصدق،
which is why, when you look at other people,
وهذا هو السبب، عندما تنظر إلى الناس الآخرين،
when you look at the person sitting next to you,
عندما تنظر إلى الشخص الذي يجلس إلى جانبك،
you don't see their skin or their face changing color.
فإنك لا تشاهد تغير ألوان جلودهم أو وجههم.
When we look at this video of Steve here, it appears to us like a static picture,
عندما ننظر إلى هذا الفيديو من ستيف، يبدو لنا وكأنه صورة ثابتة،
but once we look at this video through our new, special microscope,
ولكن عندما ننظر إلى هذا الفيديو من خلال مجهرنا الخاص الجديد،
suddenly we see a completely different image.
نفاجأ بأننا نرى صورة مختلفة تماما.
What you see here are small changes in the color of Steve's skin,
ما تراه هنا هو تغييرات صغيرة في لون جلد ستيف،
magnified 100 times so that they become visible.
مكبرة 100 مرة بحيث تكون مرئية.
We can actually see a human pulse.
باستطاعتنا ،في الحقيقة، رؤية نبض الإنسان.
We can see how fast Steve's heart is beating,
يمكننا أن نرى مدى سرعة ضربات قلب ستيف،
but we can also see the actual way that the blood flows in his face.
ولكن يمكننا أيضاً رؤية طريقة تدفق الدم الفعلي إلى وجه ستيف.
And we can do that not just to visualize the pulse,
ويمكننا أن نفعل أكثر من إظهار النبض،
but also to actually recover our heart rates,
ولكن أيضا لاستعادة معدل ضربات قلوبنا،
and measure our heart rates.
وقياس معدل ضربات قلوبنا
And we can do it with regular cameras and without touching the patients.
ويمكننا ان نعمل ذلك بالكاميرات العادية وبدون لمس المرضى.
So here you see the pulse and heart rate we extracted from a neonatal baby
هكذا كما ترون معدل النبض ومعدل نبض القلب، التي اخذناها من طفل حديث الولادة
from a video we took with a regular DSLR camera,
من شريط فيديو اخذنا بكاميرا الرقمية العادية،
and the heart rate measurement we get
وحصلنا على قياس معدل ضربات القلب
is as accurate as the one you'd get with a standard monitor in a hospital.
وحصلنا على قياس معدل ضربات القلب بنفس الدقة؛ كما لو قمت به في بالجهاز المخصص في المستشفى.
And it doesn't even have to be a video we recorded.
ولا يستلزم استخدام مقطع فيديو قمنا بتسجيله
We can do it essentially with other videos as well.
بل يمكننا أيضا استخدام أي مقطع فيديو آخر
So I just took a short clip from "Batman Begins" here
لذلك أخذت مقطع قصير من فلم "الرجل الوطواط يبدأ"
just to show Christian Bale's pulse.
فقط لاظهار نبض كريستيان بايل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you know, presumably he's wearing makeup,
وكما تعرفون، مفترضاً، انه يضع ماكياج،
the lighting here is kind of challenging,
الإضاءة هنا فيها نوع من التحدي،
but still, just from the video, we're able to extract his pulse
ولكن ما زالنا، بواسطة شريط الفيديو، قادرون على معرفة نبضه
and show it quite well.
وإظهارها بشكل جيد نسبياً.
So how do we do all that?
إذاً كيف نفعل كل ذلك؟
We basically analyze the changes in the light that are recorded
ببساطة، نقوم بتحليل التغييرات في الضوء والتي قمنا بتسجيلها
at every pixel in the video over time,
ومع مرور الوقت نكون قد حللنا كل بكسل
and then we crank up those changes.
وبعد ذلك، نقوم برفع هذه التغييرات
We make them bigger so that we can see them.
فنقوم بتكبيرها، لنتمكن من رؤيتها
The tricky part is that those signals,
الجزء المحير هو تلك الإشارات
those changes that we're after, are extremely subtle,
هذه التغييرات، التي نحن نتابعها، خفية للغاية،
so we have to be very careful when you try to separate them
لذلك علينا التروي عندما نريد تفريقهم
from noise that always exists in videos.
من الضوضاء التي تحدث في مقاطع الفيديو.
So we use some clever image processing techniques
لذلك نقوم باستخدام تقنيات ذكية لمعالجة الصور
to get a very accurate measurement of the color at each pixel in the video,
للحصول على معدل قياس دقيق للون في كل بكسل في مقطع الفيديو،
and then the way the color changes over time,
وبعد ذلك، يتغير اللون مع الوقت،
and then we amplify those changes.
ثم نقوم بتضخيم هذه التغيرات.
We make them bigger to create those types of enhanced videos, or magnified videos,
نقوم بتكبيرها لنصنع هذه الأنواع المطورة او الضخمة من مقاطع الفيديو
that actually show us those changes.
وهذا في الحقيقة يبرز لنا التغيرات
But it turns out we can do that not just to show tiny changes in color,
ولكن اتضح لنا ان باستطاعتنا إبراز ليس فقط التغيرات الدقيقة في اللون
but also tiny motions,
بل كذلك الحركات الدقيقة،
and that's because the light that gets recorded in our cameras
وهذا بسبب أن الضوء المسجل بكاميراتنا
will change not only if the color of the object changes,
لن يغير فقط لون الجسم المتغيرة،
but also if the object moves.
بل حتى تحرك الجسم.
So this is my daughter when she was about two months old.
والآن.. هذه بنتي عندما كان عمرها شهرين.
It's a video I recorded about three years ago.
ومقطع الفيديو هذا قمت بتسجيله منذ ثلاث سنوات.
And as new parents, we all want to make sure our babies are healthy,
وكوالدين جديدين، نريد كلناأن نبقي اطفالنا بصحة جيدة.
that they're breathing, that they're alive, of course.
يتنفسون جيداً، وأنهم احياء بالطبع.
So I too got one of those baby monitors
لذلك حصلت على اجهزة مراقبة الأطفال
so that I could see my daughter when she was asleep.
لتمكنني من مراقبة طفلتي وهي نائمة.
And this is pretty much what you'll see with a standard baby monitor.
وهذا إلى حد كبير ما ترونه مسجلاً من هذا الجهاز.
You can see the baby's sleeping, but there's not too much information there.
أنتم تشاهدن الطفلة نائمة، ولكن دون معلومات معتبرة عنها.
There's not too much we can see.
لا يوجد ما يستحق ملاحظته.
Wouldn't it be better, or more informative, or more useful,
هل من الأفضل أو المفيد
if instead we could look at the view like this.
إن شاهدنا المنظر بهذه الشكل.
So here I took the motions and I magnified them 30 times,
لذلك قمت بتكبير التحركات 30 مرة.
and then I could clearly see that my daughter was indeed alive and breathing.
لأتمكن من مشاهدة طفلتي حية ترزق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here is a side-by-side comparison.
هنا المقارنة جنباً إلى جنب.
So again, in the source video, in the original video,
مرة اخرى إن كان مقطع الفيديو هو الأصلي،
there's not too much we can see,
فلا يوجد ما يمكن ملاحظته،
but once we magnify the motions, the breathing becomes much more visible.
ولكن عندما نقوم بتكبير الحركات، فإننا سنلاحظها بوضوح.
And it turns out, there's a lot of phenomena
ويتضح لنا وجود الكثير من الظواهر
we can reveal and magnify with our new motion microscope.
ويمكننا إبراز وتكبير بواسطة مجهر
We can see how our veins and arteries are pulsing in our bodies.
نستطيع مشاهدة كيف تنبض أوردتها وشرياننا في أجسادنا.
We can see that our eyes are constantly moving
نستطيع مشاهدة الحركة الثابتة لعينينا
in this wobbly motion.
في هذه الحركة المتذبذبة.
And that's actually my eye,
وهذه في الحقيقة عيني،
and again this video was taken right after my daughter was born,
وهذا مرة أخرى مقطع فيديو مسجل بعد ولادة طفلتي،
so you can see I wasn't getting too much sleep. (Laughter)
لذلك تلاحظون اني لم أنم جيداً. (ضحك)
Even when a person is sitting still,
حتى عندما يبقى الشخص جالساً،
there's a lot of information we can extract
يوجد الكثير من المعلومات التي يمكن استخراجها
about their breathing patterns, small facial expressions.
عن أنواع التنفس، وتعابير الوجه الدقيقة.
Maybe we could use those motions
من الممكن استخدام هذه الحركات
to tell us something about our thoughts or our emotions.
لمعرفة افكارنا ومشاعرنا.
We can also magnify small mechanical movements,
وأيضاً بإمكاننا تكبير الحركة الصغيرة الميكانيكية،
like vibrations in engines,
مثل الاهتزازات في المحركات،
that can help engineers detect and diagnose machinery problems,
والتي من الممكن ان تساعد المهندسين لاكتشاف وتشخيص المشاكل الآلية،
or see how our buildings and structures sway in the wind and react to forces.
أو مشاهدة كيف تتأثر المباني والمنشآت من الرياح ومقاومتها للقوة.
Those are all things that our society knows how to measure in various ways,
هذه هي الأشياء التي يعلم مجتمعنا كيف يقيسها بعدة طرق،
but measuring those motions is one thing,
لكن قياس هذه الحركات شيء،
and actually seeing those motions as they happen
ومشاهدة هذه الحراكات كما تحدث
is a whole different thing.
شيءٌ اخر تماماً.
And ever since we discovered this new technology,
ومنذ اكتشافنا لهذه التقنية الجديدة،
we made our code available online so that others could use and experiment with it.
وفرنا الرمز في الشبكة العنكبوتية ليتمكن الناس من استخدامها وتجريبها.
It's very simple to use.
إنه من السهل استخدامها.
It can work on your own videos.
يمكنك العمل عليها بمقاطع الفيديو الخاص بك.
Our collaborators at Quanta Research even created this nice website
مساعدينا في البحوث الكمية أنشأوا موقع رائع
where you can upload your videos and process them online,
والتي يمكنك رفع مقاطع الفيديو ومعالجتها في الانترنت،
so even if you don't have any experience in computer science or programming,
حتى لو لم يكن عندك خبره في استخدام الحاسب وبرامجه،
you can still very easily experiment with this new microscope.
يمكنك بسهولة استعماله بهذا المجهر الجديد.
And I'd like to show you just a couple of examples
واضرب لكم مثالين فقط
of what others have done with it.
كيف استخدمت.
So this video was made by a YouTube user called Tamez85.
مقطع اليوتيوب هذا، سُجل من تامس 85
I don't know who that user is,
في الحقيقة لا اعرف هذا المستخدم،
but he, or she, used our code
لكنه او لكنها استخدمت برنامجنا
to magnify small belly movements during pregnancy.
لتكبير حركة البطن الدقيقة أثناء الحمل.
It's kind of creepy.
إنها مخيفة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
People have used it to magnify pulsing veins in their hands.
يستخدم الناس الجهاز لتكبير تنصرت الشرايين في أيديهم.
And you know it's not real science unless you use guinea pigs,
وأنتم تعرفون انها ليست علمية، ما لم تستخدم الخنزير المنقرض في جنوب قارة امريكا،
and apparently this guinea pig is called Tiffany,
ومن الظاهر ان هذا الخنزير يدعى تفني،
and this YouTube user claims it is the first rodent on Earth
ويدعي هذا المستخدم انه اول منقرض على الارض
that was motion-magnified.
كانت هذه حركة مكبرة.
You can also do some art with it.
يمكنك أيضاً استخدام الفن بها.
So this video was sent to me by a design student at Yale.
هذا المقطع أرسل لي من طالب تصميم من جامعة ييل.
She wanted to see if there's any difference
انها تريد معرفة ما اذا كان هناك اختلاف.
in the way her classmates move.
في تحركات زملاءها بالجامعة.
She made them all stand still, and then magnified their motions.
طلبت منهم الوقوف ثابتين لكي تتمكن من تكبير حركتهم.
It's like seeing still pictures come to life.
إنها تشبه الصور الثابتة التي تبعث للحياة.
And the nice thing with all those examples
وأجمل ما في هذين المثالين
is that we had nothing to do with them.
اننا لا يمكن ان نتصرف بهما.
We just provided this new tool, a new way to look at the world,
نحن فقط نزودك بأدواتنا لتتمكن من رؤية العالم بطريقة جديدة،
and then people find other interesting, new and creative ways of using it.
والنَّاس بعد ذلك سيجدون طرق أخرى مثيرة وجديدة وإبداعيةلاستخدامها.
But we didn't stop there.
ولكن لم نتوقف عند ذلك.
This tool not only allows us to look at the world in a new way,
هذه الاداة لم تسمح لنا بالنظر للعالم بطريقة جديدة أيضاً،
it also redefines what we can do
نستطيع إعادة تحديد ما يمكننا عمله
and pushes the limits of what we can do with our cameras.
ودفع حدود ما يمكننا عمله بكاميراتنا.
So as scientists, we started wondering,
لذلك كعلماء، بدأنا نتسآئل،
what other types of physical phenomena produce tiny motions
ما هي أنواع المظاهر الفيزيائية التي تنتج هذه الحركات الدقيقة
that we could now use our cameras to measure?
والتي نستطيع بكاميراتنا قياسها؟
And one such phenomenon that we focused on recently is sound.
وإحدى المظاهر التي نركز عليها حالياً هو الصوت.
Sound, as we all know, is basically changes
الصوت، كما نعرف، مُتَغير
in air pressure that travel through the air.
بواسطة ضغط الهواء، والذي ينتقل عن طريق الهواء.
Those pressure waves hit objects and they create small vibrations in them,
فيضرب الضغط الأجسام، تقوم بإنشاء تردد صغير بداخلها،
which is how we hear and how we record sound.
وهذا يوضح ما نسمعه وما نسجله.
But it turns out that sound also produces visual motions.
واتضح كذلك أن الصوت ينتج حركات مرئيّة.
Those are motions that are not visible to us
هذه الحركات لا نستطيع مشاهدتها
but are visible to a camera with the right processing.
لكنها مرئيّة للكاميرا مع المعالج المناسب.
So here are two examples.
والآن يوجد مثالين.
This is me demonstrating my great singing skills.
هذا أنا اجرب مهارات صوتي العظيم
(Singing)
(غناء)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I took a high-speed video of my throat while I was humming.
وأخذت مقطع مسّرع لحلقي وأنا أهمهم.
Again, if you stare at that video,
مرة اخرى، ان قمت بالتركيز في مقطع الفيديو هذا،
there's not too much you'll be able to see,
فلا يمكن أن تشاهد ما يلفت الانتباه،
but once we magnify the motions 100 times, we can see all the motions and ripples
ولكن عندما نكبر الصور 100 ضعفاً، فإننا نتمكن من مشاهدة كل الحركات التموجات
in the neck that are involved in producing the sound.
في العنق الذي يشارك في إنتاج الصوت.
That signal is there in that video.
تلك الإشارة في مقطع الفيديو هذا.
We also know that singers can break a wine glass
ونعرف أيضاً أن المغنين يستطيع كسر كأس من الخمر
if they hit the correct note.
إذا تمكنوا من العزف على الوتر الحساس.
So here, we're going to play a note
والآن، سنقوم بعزف نوتة
that's in the resonance frequency of that glass
تردد صدى الكأس هذا
through a loudspeaker that's next to it.
من مكبر الصوت الذي بجانبه.
Once we play that note and magnify the motions 250 times,
وعندما نعزف النوتة ونكبر الحركات 250 مرة،
we can very clearly see how the glass vibrates
نستطيع بوضوح تاماً أن نرى كيف يتذبذب الكأس
and resonates in response to the sound.
والصدى في استجابة للصوت.
It's not something you're used to seeing every day.
إنه ليس من المعتاد مشاهدته يوميًا.
But this made us think. It gave us this crazy idea.
لكن هذا حثنا على التفكير. اعطانا الفكرة المجنونة هذه.
Can we actually invert this process and recover sound from video
هل يمكننا قلب هذه العملية واسترجاع الصوت من الفيديو
by analyzing the tiny vibrations that sound waves create in objects,
بواسطة التذبذبات الدقيقة والتي ينشؤها تموج الصوت في الأجسام،
and essentially convert those back into the sounds that produced them.
و نقل الصوت الذي ينتجهم.
In this way, we can turn everyday objects into microphones.
بهذه الطريقة، باستطاعتنا تحويل الأجسام في المايكروفونات.
So that's exactly what we did.
وهذا بالضبط ما عملناه.
So here's an empty bag of chips that was lying on a table,
والآن، هنا كيس فارغ من رقائق البطاطس الموضوع على الطاولة،
and we're going to turn that bag of chips into a microphone
وستحول هذا الكيس إلى مايكروفون
by filming it with a video camera
من خلال تسجيله بالكاميرا
and analyzing the tiny motions that sound waves create in it.
وتحليل التحركات الدقيقة، المكّونة من تموجات الصوت بداخله.
So here's the sound that we played in the room.
والآن، هذا هو الصوت الذي شغلناه في الغرفة.
(Music: "Mary Had a Little Lamb")
(موسيقى)
And this is a high-speed video we recorded of that bag of chips.
وهذا فيديو مسّرع ومسجل في الكيس.
Again it's playing.
مرة اخرى، تشغيل الصوت.
There's no chance you'll be able to see anything going on in that video
لا يوجد فرصة لمشاهدة أي شيء في مقطع الفيديو
just by looking at it,
بمجرد رؤيته،
but here's the sound we were able to recover just by analyzing
ولكن نستطيعوا استعادة هذا الصوت بمجرد تحليل
the tiny motions in that video.
تحركاته الدقيقة في الفيديو.
(Music: "Mary Had a Little Lamb")
(موسيقى)
I call it -- Thank you.
انا اطلق عليه... شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I call it the visual microphone.
انا اطلق عليه المايكرفون المرئي.
We actually extract audio signals from video signals.
في الحقيقة، استخرجنا الإشارات الصوتية من إشارات الفيديو.
And just to give you a sense of the scale of the motions here,
ولاعطاءكم فكرة عن مقدار الحركات هنا،
a pretty loud sound will cause that bag of chips to move less than a micrometer.
الصوت العالي نسبيا سوف يتسبب بحركة الكيس باقل من مايكروميتر.
That's one thousandth of a millimeter.
هذا واحد على الألف مليمتر.
That's how tiny the motions are that we are now able to pull out
هذه دقة الحركات، والتي استطعنا استخرجها
just by observing how light bounces off objects
بملاحظة فقط كيف يتردد الضوء خارج الأجسام
and gets recorded by our cameras.
وتسجيله بكاميرتنا
We can recover sounds from other objects, like plants.
نستطيع استخراج الصوت من أجسام اخرى كالشجر
(Music: "Mary Had a Little Lamb")
(موسيقى)
And we can recover speech as well.
وتستطيع استرجاع الخطاب كذلك.
So here's a person speaking in a room.
هنا شخص يتحدث في الغرفة.
Voice: Mary had a little lamb whose fleece was white as snow,
صوت: ماري تملك خروف صغير، صوفه ابيض كالثلج،
and everywhere that Mary went, that lamb was sure to go.
واينما ذهبت ماري، يتبعها الخروف.
Michael Rubinstein: And here's that speech again recovered
مايكل روبنسون: والآن الكلام بعد استخراجه
just from this video of that same bag of chips.
فقط من خلال هذا الفيديو من نفس كيس البطاطس.
Voice: Mary had a little lamb whose fleece was white as snow,
صوت: ماري تملك خروف صغير، صوفه ابيض كالثلج،
and everywhere that Mary went, that lamb was sure to go.
واينما ذهبت ماري، يتبعها الخروف.
MR: We used "Mary Had a Little Lamb"
السيد: نحن استخدمنا "ماري تملك خروف صغير"
because those are said to be the first words
لأن هذه الكلمات قيلت لتكون الأُولى
that Thomas Edison spoke into his phonograph in 1877.
من توماس إديسون من خلال نسجله في عام 1877.
It was one of the first sound recording devices in history.
إنه أول صوت مسجل بأجهزة في التاريخ.
It basically directed the sounds onto a diaphragm
إنه ببساطة توجيه الصوت إلى طبلة الهاتف
that vibrated a needle that essentially engraved the sound on tinfoil
والتي هزت الابرة المثبتة أساساً للصوت على صفيحة الألمونيوم
that was wrapped around the cylinder.
والملفوفة حول الأسطوانة.
Here's a demonstration of recording and replaying sound with Edison's phonograph.
هنا مثال لعملية تسجيل وإعادة تشغيل الصوت من مسجل إديسون.
(Video) Voice: Testing, testing, one two three.
(فيديو) صوت: اختبار، اختبار، واحد، اثنين، ثلاثة.
Mary had a little lamb whose fleece was white as snow,
ماري تملك خروف صغير، صوفه ابيض كالثلج،
and everywhere that Mary went, the lamb was sure to go.
واينما ذهبت ماري، يتبعها الخروف.
Testing, testing, one two three.
صوت: اختبار، اختبار، واحد، اثنين، ثلاثة.
Mary had a little lamb whose fleece was white as snow,
ماري تملك خروف صغير، صوفه ابيض كالثلج،
and everywhere that Mary went, the lamb was sure to go.
واينما ذهبت ماري، يتبعها الخروف.
MR: And now, 137 years later,
السيد: والآن بعد 137'
we're able to get sound in pretty much similar quality
بإمكاننا الحصول على الصوت نفس جودة الصوت تقريباً
but by just watching objects vibrate to sound with cameras,
ولكن بمجرد مشاهدة الأجسام المهتزة من الصوت عن طريق الكاميرا
and we can even do that when the camera
بإمكاننا عمل ذلك عندما تكون الكاميرا
is 15 feet away from the object, behind soundproof glass.
على بعد 15 قدم من الجسم، خلف الزجاج العازل للصوت.
So this is the sound that we were able to recover in that case.
وهذا هو الصوت الذي تمكنا من استخراجه في هذا الأمر.
Voice: Mary had a little lamb whose fleece was white as snow,
صوت: ماري تملك خروف صغير، صوفه ابيض كالثلج،
and everywhere that Mary went, the lamb was sure to go.
واينما ذهبت ماري، يتبعها الخروف.
MR: And of course, surveillance is the first application that comes to mind.
السيد: وبالطبع، الرقابة اول شيء يخطر على البال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But it might actually be useful for other things as well.
ولكن من المحتمل أن تكون مفيدة من نواحي أخرى أيضاً.
Maybe in the future, we'll be able to use it, for example,
ربما في المستقبل نستطيع ان نستخدمها على سبيل المثال،
to recover sound across space,
لمعرفة الأصوات القادمة من الفضاء،
because sound can't travel in space, but light can.
لأن الصوت لا يمكنه الانتقال عبر الفضاء، بعكس الضوء.
We've only just begun exploring
نحن لتونا بدانا بالاكتشاف
other possible uses for this new technology.
الأسباب الاخرى المُحتملة لاستخدام هذه التقنية الجديدة.
It lets us see physical processes that we know are there
إنها تمكننا من مشاهدة العمليات الفيزيائية والتي نعلم وجودها
but that we've never been able to see with our own eyes until now.
ولكن لم نتمكن من مشاهدتها بأعيننا حتى الان.
This is our team.
هذا هو فريقنا.
Everything I showed you today is a result of a collaboration
كل ما شاهدتموه هو نتيجة من تعاوننا
with this great group of people you see here,
مع فريق العمل العظيم الذي تنظرن إليه،
and I encourage you and welcome you to check out our website,
وأشجعكم وأرحب بكم للتحقق من موقعنا،
try it out yourself,
بتجردها بأنفسكم،
and join us in exploring this world of tiny motions.
وانضموا لنا في استكشاف عالم الحركات الدقيقة.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)